Okay, before heading to the slides for this week,
I want to do a short video about basically
debugging a small Haskell program.
So, this is motivated by an email I got from one student in
the last few days about task 12 (actually, in a previous year),
there was this program for which a
student didn't know why it wasn't working.
And well, the point is not to
point out this wrong program.
But actually, the conversation we then had over
email was very interesting, in terms of suggesting
how to approach such problems; then I thought it
would be nice to demonstrate this here also in a
short video so that you can also maybe get an
idea of how you could cope with similar problems.
I hope the student won't be annoyed
that I used their example here.
Okay, anyway, so this was the program
that the student had at that point,
and the student already knew that something was
wrong because the test suite was not working.
So, let me actually reproduce
this and call the test suite.
Okay, so that was an error in the second
test, which I have actually abbreviated.
So, there was a long description
here in the test suite,
of what this second test means. But
apparently, it fails for some inputs.
Okay.
And so, what does this mean; how to interpret
this... Well, to see what's happening here,
we can actually see what input
the function is called on here.
We can see that, basically, the character
is appended to a string, which is also
a short string here, the one-element string,
and then the character is appended again.
So, apparently, this property
failed for something of the form:
we can simply call this "aba"; where there
was some string "b" and 'a' was appended
at the beginning and at the end. And for
this, somehow, the property seems to fail.
And indeed, if we call this function as given
above, and it says that "aba" is not a palindrome,
whereas we know that it
is, so something is wrong.
And the student already said something like, they
have thought about the problem in the cases.
And the first case you have, of course, fine,
it's checking for short strings,
which are definitely palindromes.
And then there was an idea here, about reversing
the list and then comparing it piecewise using
the capitalization via toUpper, and the students
thought, well, this should work in their mind.
They have worked out that this
runs okay, but apparently doesn't.
And the question would be
what to do in such a case.
Okay, so you need to debug.
Now, coming from an imperative
programming background,
most of you probably think of debugging in
terms of adding print statements to your code,
right; you have some code, a loop, maybe you
want to know what's happening in the loop.
So, you add a print statement that prints
out a loop counter or some other variables.
Now, that's not something that we
can really do in Haskell immediately
because we do expression-based
programming, not command-based programming.
There is no place in a sequence of commands
where somehow you can insert a print statement.
That simply isn't the way this program works.
So, not only do we have a different
programming paradigm and a different testing
paradigm, as we saw last week, by going from
unit tests to property tests. You also need, or
we can employ, a different debugging paradigm.
So, what would debugging mean here?
Since computation is always
happening via expressions, the proper
idea is to inspect expressions for somehow
knowing that for this three-element string,
we will go into the second case here.
The question would be: What value does this
expression have when we call
this as being this "aba"?
Yes, because probably the
student had some expectation
that this should evaluate to
true because it is a palindrome.
But for whatever reason, this actually
evaluated to False, as we see here.
So, then we could dig deeper and find
out "what about subexpressions", right?
Expressions are compositional.
So, if an expression doesn't give the proper
value, then either you have used the wrong
function, maybe this "and" is wrong and
could be an "or", or something else.
Or maybe the arguments are wrong. Because
everything is compositional, these are
basically the only two choices, or the only
two reasons why the outcome could be wrong.
So, what we need to do is to dive into these
expressions and see where something comes up,
that is not expected.
And if you think back to the very first
lecture where I worked with CodeWorld,
there was this nice feature that
you could inspect an expression.
So, you had a drawn picture, and you could select
subexpressions and see what picture they generate.
Now in this visual way, in CodeWorld's surroundings,
that's, of course, a very nice inspection facility
for all kinds of debugging.
Of course, this doesn't work here because
we don't have a picture that we can click.
So, instead, we have to work with the interpreter
and produce subexpressions that are of
interest and see what they evaluate to.
So, how can we do this?
Well, for this, you should
really not just work in Autotool,
you should have an interpreter on your
machine in order to be able to do this.
Okay, we want to know what this
expression evaluates to, and why
it does, and for these particular inputs.
What we actually want to have is: we want to
evaluate this expression, but in the context where
s, the input, is our failing input "aba", and
s' is whatever was computed from it, right,
because s and s' occur in this expression.
So, we can't simply type this expression.
If I just type this expression
into the interpreter prompt,
I get an error because the
s and s' are unknown.
Okay, now, so in the interpreter
session, you can simply
provide values, you can open the scope, you can
say, well, I want to check this property here,
for the case that s is my original input, "aba",
because that's what's happening with this case.
What we can say here is `let s = "aba"`.
Now, this is like a 'let ... in'
in function equations.
But the scope is now for the
rest of the interpreter session,
instead of for the right-hand side
of a function. Okay, I can do this.
And then I can actually also do this.
I can simply copy this line from here,
because I also want the s' to be
in scope of exactly the kind of computation
that happens in the program at this point.
Okay, so now I have s in
scope and have s' in scope.
Okay, they have the expected values.
And now the question
would be, what does this evaluate to and why
doesn't it evaluate to True, as one could expect?
Indeed, it evaluates to False, calling
isPalindrome on "aba" is False.
But then the question is, well, why is that?
And the only way to investigate this is
to go deeper and take this subexpression
and check what this evaluates to.
Yes, that's the compositional debugging here.
So, this evaluates to a
list of some Trues and some
Falses, and that's probably
not what the student intended.
Probably the student also didn't
expect that there would be nine
values; of course, the student
eventually repaired their program.
So, maybe this is also the thought process that
went into this, but it doesn't really matter.
The point is, at this point, one could
realize that something is going wrong,
because we have these nine results.
Yes, actually, the idea was to take this
three-element String and compare element-wise.
So, we should only have 3 Boolean values.
Something is wrong; what is wrong?
Well, you could go deeper by finding
out or outputting not exactly this
check here, but actually the values
of x and y that are used in there.
So, we could, for example,
simply output the pair (x,y).
And then we see what's going wrong.
We don't compare 'a' to 'a', 'b' to 'b', 'a' to
'a', but we compare everything to everything, right?
That's why we have nine comparisons.
And also some of them are wrong,
even though we have a palindrome.
Okay, so at this point, I think it becomes
obvious what the—maybe the errors I’m
thinking about the problem were, where we
don't want to, in the list comprehension,
draw the x and y variables from s and s'
independently; we want to draw them in lockstep.
So, the first one from s, the first
one from s' and the second one from s
and the second one from s', et cetera.
This is not what it is doing here. What this
is doing is building a Cartesian product.
That's also what the student realized, probably.
Okay, so now what if you need something
else? And if you go back to the slides,
you'll find actually some
examples for doing just that.
So, one way to do this, to get the pairwise
corresponding elements from s and s' in the
list comprehension, is to not have two generators
for x and y, but to have a combined generator
for pairs, and it runs over the
zipping (using 'zip') of s and s'.
Okay, and if you would check
this now, then it would both
work in the examples and
also pass the test suite.
Okay, story finished; this would now be a
repair of the program found by this debugging
setup with inspecting
subexpressions in the interpreter.
Okay, then I also want to show another way.
It may be a more familiar way to you,
which somewhat corresponds to this inserting of
print statements, but it's not exactly that.
And I want to show this so that you could use
it if you encounter problems in your exercises.
For this reason, I go back to the original wrong
program and try a different debugging strategy.
So, again, I can load this, and it is wrong.
It's failing for exactly
the same reason as before.
Still wrong on this input.
And now what is this other way of debugging?
Well, one could attempt or could be tempted
to do this printing out of values of
subexpressions on the run while the program is
running and not in a separate interpreter run.
That's not in a session as added here.
And there are some facilities for doing this.
And in order to do this, you will need to import
the debugging module, and then in this module,
you could find the implementation of various
functions that can be used for debugging.
And well, I will simply now use the
one that I know will work in this case,
in general, you would have to make
a good decision about what to do.
Okay.
And so, the idea here is I want to print or
I want to see the value of this expression,
when it's encountered.
Okay, and there is a function in said
module with a cryptic name somewhat.
So, what does it do? I simply add
it to the program at this point.
And then I go back and load
the module and run this again.
Now I get two Falses, and the first False
is actually when this subexpression was
encountered and computed, and then of
course, the final output is also False.
That's why we have two Falses; the first
False is from printing the subexpression.
And the second False is from printing
the outcome of the function call,
which in this case is, of course,
also the whole subexpression.
That's why we have two Falses.
But then I could again, go deeper
and see, well, why is it False?
What was actually the list that was used here?
Yes, so I move inside the expression; I reload
my module, I call it—call the function again.
And now I see what the value was at that point. And
it is again, the same wrong nine element list instead
of a three-element list with some Trues and some
Falses, which ultimately led to the outcome False.
Okay, then I could go deeper
and say, well, why is that?
Yes, so how do these values appear?
So, maybe I even want to do the trace inside here
to directly see the result of the comparison here.
I reload this.
I run this.
Okay.
Now, this is interesting.
We don't get nine values now; why not?
Well, because of lazy evaluation.
Yes.
So, the list that would be computed in
this subexpression here would consist of
all these nine values, and when I actually
use the and combinator to do a Boolean and
over a list of values, then, of course,
this can stop as soon as a False is seen.
And that's what you see in action here.
So, if I say I always want to output
the result of this comparison,
while the program is running, you see that
actually from this nine element list here
only the first True is output,
then this second False is output,
and all the remaining values will be never
computed, so these comparisons never happen.
But anyway, the final outcome is False,
because even after seeing True and False,
the and function knows that
the final output is False.
So, it's still the same error
as before; you now simply better
see which of these comparisons are
actually performed on the first two.
And you could make this more apparent
by using a slightly different
trace function here, and
instead of outputting the result
of the comparison, actually output the
values that go into the comparison.
If I trace this now,
then I actually see that first 'a' and 'a' are
compared, which is probably what was expected
when this program was written, but then 'a' and 'b'
are compared, and this is why this is deemed not to
be a palindrome because this 'a' and this 'b' are
compared, or maybe this 'b' and this 'a', I don't know.
Anyway, something is not lining up and
the comparison compares things
that shouldn't be compared.
And then maybe at this point, one could
say, could realize what the problem is,
we know already what the problem was, right?
The problem was that we shouldn't draw
x and y from s and s' independently,
but actually, we should draw both of them
at once, from the zipping of s and s'.
Okay.
And if I now run this with my debug annotation,
I see that actually I get exactly three
comparisons: 'a' compared to 'a', 'b' to 'b', 'a' to
'a'. As expected, all of these comparisons are true.
That's why also the final output is True.
Okay, and now probably I fixed my problem,
I could, of course, run the test suite.
This will give many outputs because
now I run the test suite while
also outputting all these characters,
these very strange characters,
some special characters that
are simply generated at random.
So, probably I don't want this ultimately, I of
course, want to get rid of my tracing again.
So, I want to have the pure solution.
Also, because of the debugging, you can't submit
this to Autotool, so you have to take it out again.
But now, we hopefully have a program that is
correct, and indeed it passes the test suite.
Okay, I hope this is useful if you
encounter problems in some tasks,
don't simply try to hammer away in Autotool,
but actually work offline and use facilities
like the interpreter to really investigate what your
program is doing and run some examples, etcetera.